Eugene Edwin Johnston Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Eugene Edwin Johnston Papers 1912-2008 (bulk 1940-1963)
MSS85926
Johnston, Eugene Edwin, 1915-2006
2,000 items
4 containers plus 1 oversize
1.6 linear feet
182 digital files (9.68 GB)
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Army officer. Correpondence, military papers, writings, photographs, awards, certificates, maps, printed matter, digital files, and other papers relating to Johnston's military career, particularly his service with the 92nd Infantry Division during World War II.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Johnston family.; Johnston, Alta Ross, 1919-2000--Correspondence.; Johnston, Carolyn, 1948- --Correspondence.; Johnston, Eugene Edwin, 1915-2006.; Smith, Nancy Johnston, 1945- --Correspondence.
Organizations
United States. Army--African American troops.; United States. Army--Foreign service--Austria.; United States. Army--Foreign service--Taiwan.; United States. Army--Foreign service--Thailand.; United States. Army--Medals, badges, decorations, etc.; United States. Army. Infantry Division, 92nd.; United States. Army. Infantry Regiment, 350th.
Subjects
African American soldiers.; Bronze Star Medal (U.S.); Genealogy.; World War, 1939-1945--Italy.; World War, 1939-1945--Participation, African American.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.
Places
United States--Armed Forces--African Americans.; United States--Race relations.
Occupations
Army officers.
Provenance
The papers of Eugene Edwin Johnston, army officer, were given to the Library of Congress in 2014.
Transfers
Audiocassettes have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division where they are identified as part of the Eugene Edwin Johnston Papers. One book, My Father's War: Fighting with the Buffalo Soldiers in World War II, has been made available as part of the Manuscript Division Reading Room reference collection.
Related Material
Related collections in the Manuscript Division include the United States Army 92nd Infantry Division Collection.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Eugene Edwin Johnston are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Digital Format
Digital files were received as part of the papers of Eugene Edwin Johnston. Reference copies were created from the original digital media. Advanced notice is required for access to digital content; consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division for more information.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1915, Oct. 10 Born, Chattanooga, Tenn.
1933 Graduated, Chattanooga High School, Chattanooga, Tenn.
1940 Enlisted in United States Army, and assigned to medical detachment hospital, Fort Oglethorpe, Ga.
1942 Graduated, Officer Candidate School, Fort Benning, Ga. Assigned to 371st Infantry Regiment, 92nd Infantry Division, Camp Robinson, Ark.
1943 Operations and training staff officer, 92nd Infantry Division, Fort Huachuca, Ariz. Married Alta Ross
1944 1945 Served as rifle company commander and heavy weapons company commander, 92nd Infantry Division, North Apennines and Po Valley campaigns, Italy
1945 Promoted to captain Awarded Bronze Star Medal, Italy
1946 Promoted to major
1948 S-3 (Operations), 11th Infantry Regiment, 5th Infantry Division, Fort Jackson, S.C.
1950 1953 Assigned to 350th Infantry Regiment, Austria
1953 1955 Army advisor, National Guard, N.C.
1956 1957 Military advisor, Military Assistance Advisory Group, Taiwan
1958 1960 S-4 (Logistics), Combat Development Experimentation Command, 1st Brigade, 10th Infantry, Fort Ord, Calif.
1961 1962 Military advisor, Joint United States Military Advisory Group, Thailand
1962 Recalled from Thailand to assist in re-activation of 1st Armored Division, Fort Hood, Tex.
1963 Retired from U.S. Army as lieutenant colonel
2006, Mar. 12 Died, Cleveland, Tenn.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Eugene Edwin Johnston (1915-2006) span the years 1912-2008, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1940-1963. Correspondence, military papers, writings, photographs, awards, certificates, maps, printed matter, digital files, and other papers document Johnston's military career and focus on his service with the 92nd Infantry Division. The papers are in English. The collection is arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material and therein chronologically.
Johnston served with the 92nd Infantry Division, nicknamed the Buffalo Soldiers Division, during World War II, and the division saw heavy combat in northern Italy from 1944 to 1945. Included in the papers are Johnston's Buffalo Soldier patch, a publication about the division, and documentation regarding his award of a Bronze Star Medal in 1945. As a white, commanding officer in a primarily African-American unit of the segregated United States Army, Johnston wrote to his wife about his dealings with the troops. He was proud of their accomplishments and recommended some for decorations. There are glimpses of the racial dynamics and tensions in the division in Johnston's early correspondence. The full extent of Johnston's experience with the division is discussed in the oral history interviews conducted by Carolyn Johnston, daughter of Eugene Edwin Johnston, from 2001 to 2005. In 2012, Carolyn Johnston used the oral history interviews in her publication My Father's War: Fighting with the Buffalo Soldiers in World War II. The oral history interviews are located in the digital files. In addition, Johnston's military papers and personnel 201 file chronicle his service in Austria with the 350th Infantry Regiment from 1950 to 1953 and his role as a military advisor in Taiwan from 1956 to 1957 and in Thailand from 1961 to 1962.
Correspondents include Johnston's wife, Alta Ross Johnston, and his daughters, Carolyn Ross Johnston and Nancy Jean Johnston Smith. Many letters from the World War II era are in V-mail format.
The digital files mainly consist of images of Johnston's correspondence. The images were created in 2014 and are in PDF format. Not all correspondence is digitized. Also included are WAV files containing audio recordings of Johnston's oral history interviews from 2001 to 2005.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material and therein chronologically.
Container List
- 92nd Infantry Division related material, circa 1945, 2001, 2008 (Box 1)
- Bronze Star Medal award, 1945 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1938-1945, 1957-1963, 1998, 2004, (5 folders) (Box 1)
- Diary of Fred Johnston (father), 1912-1913, 1926-1928 (Box 1)
- Education and training file, 1934, 1958-1962, 1975 (Box 1)
- Genealogical file, 1979, undated (Box 1)
- Maps, 1944-1948, 1961-1963, undated See Oversize (Box 1)
- Miscellany, 1961, undated (Box 1)
- Military papers (Box 2)
  - 1940-1966, (6 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1969-1970, 1980-1984, 1991 (Box 3)
- Obituary, 2006 (Box 3)
- Oil tankers, 1975, undated (Box 3)
- Personnel 201 file, 1944-1963, (4 folders) (Box 3)
- Photograph albums, circa 1940-1963, undated, (2 folders) (Box 4)
- Photographs, circa 1940-circa 1963, undated (Box 4)
- Writings, circa 1957, 1984-1989, undated (Box 4)
- Oversize (Box OV 1)
  - Maps, 1944-1948, 1961-1963, undated (Container 1) (Box OV 1)
- Digital files, mss85926_106_001; mss85926_106_002
  - Correspondence, 1938-1945, 1961-1963
  - Oral history interview recordings, circa 2001-circa 2005